<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>zweifeln.org</title>
    <description>Gero Nagel is a queer observer and eternal student.</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2020 16:19:35 +0200</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2020 16:19:35 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.8.6</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Social Media Flat Rate</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Review: &lt;a href=&quot;https://log.dkarayiannis.eu/&quot;&gt;dkr&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-if-social-media-were-paid-on-a-flat-rate-model&quot;&gt;What if social media were paid on a flat rate model?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea itself is somewhat old. When Twitter started ads years ago I occasionally heard people suggest to pay for an ad free version. Maybe 5€/month or something.
There were porjects like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/App.net&quot;&gt;app.net&lt;/a&gt; that charged their users … and ultimately failed.&lt;br /&gt;
Though they charged all users for the service they provided - not for the service other users provided. That was always seen as a free gift.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the years influencers became quite a thing. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.patreon.com/&quot;&gt;Patreon&lt;/a&gt; and fundraisers like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gofundme.com/&quot;&gt;GoFundMe&lt;/a&gt; got pretty popular too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The porn scene is shifiting to &lt;a href=&quot;https://onlyfans.com/&quot;&gt;OnlyFans&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://justfor.fans/&quot;&gt;JustFor.Fans&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;creation-needs-financing&quot;&gt;Creation needs financing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What that tells me: it’s not just the servers that need payment. It’s also the content creators. Creation is a job and needs to be paid somehow. Social media became an advertising platform not just the tech companies but also for the creators. They use their social media to sell things too - may it be the product they are paid for to advertise, patreon, gofundme or their onlyfans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if social media would be a flatrate model not just for paying the tech and servers, but also the creators?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OnlyFans pays 80% of their income to their creators and keeps 20% for their own operating costs. On OnlyFans, there’s a “per channel subscription” with highly varying prices.
So, before subscribing to a new channel one does have to think about whether one channel alone is worth it. If you want to support several artists, it easily gets expensive.
It’s quite similar on Patreon. Often, there are different pledge tiers offering different perks. Those who pay more get more “behind the scenes” stuff, early access to content, or access to restricted chat platforms. How about not having “big spenders” but rather many supporters?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buying content online isn’t new. One of the biggest content-creating companies these days does not sell any content. It streams it. On a flat rate model.
Streaming services became so incredible successful because they are easy to use. If you want to watch a movie, you don’t have to buy it. You don’t have to burden of handling a credit card every time you want to watch something.&lt;br /&gt;
And semi-legal streaming sites that were very popular 10 years ago didn’t (only) disappear because of harsh copyright enforecement, but because they are annoying. Ads are annoying. Netflix is less annoying. There is neither a wall of ads to fight, nor does it make one find their credit card every time one wants to watch something. 
It is a reasonable priced streaming service, with a wide range of things one can watch and quite easy to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if social media became similar to that? What if the internet people we like would be just supported by us following them? Not just in some emotional way but actually substantially so they are able to pay their bills with just the money they make by us enjoying their content?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;follow-and-pay-people-you-like&quot;&gt;Follow and pay people you like&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Between all the ads social media - particularely Twitter - became a toxic shithole. There’s a huge political fight on the whole platform.&lt;br /&gt;
There are many opinions regarding whether the platform itself should take a stronger stand or whether it’s freedom of speech.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twitter and Facebook value debate more that support. Comments rank higher than likes or shares/retweets. The common explanation is, that comments make people stay longer on the platform and the longer people stay on the platform the more ads the platform can sell. So, social media these days are meant to create debates. They are meant to create fights. The toxic shithole it became is wanted as it creates revenue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Enemy observation” is a thing. Observe what the people you hate do, so you can react faster to whatever wrongdoing they commit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, what would happen if we were to pay the people we follow? All of them?&lt;br /&gt;
Would you still follow your enemies knowing you would have to pay them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I guess it would mean the “enemy observation” would disappear. No one would give money to people they see as their enemies.&lt;br /&gt;
It sure does not solve all political debates. But maybe it would make social media less toxic by removing “enemy observation”, as well as ads. (Ads are, after all, annoying and annoyance easily becomes aggression that will influence the platform itself.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;public-sphere-needs-to-be-owned-by-the-public&quot;&gt;Public sphere needs to be owned by the public&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social media is however quite the public sphere these days. There are many debates about companies like Facebook, Twitter and Youtube being gatekeepers to the public sphere. Particularely in a pandemic world where human gatherings have become health risks, we are even more dependant on some kind of social media to conntect and to keep the public debate alive. So, pushing them more into another for-profit model doesn’t seen reasonable to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what if that social media flatrate wouldn’t be platform-specific but rather protocol-specific?&lt;br /&gt;
What if there wouldn’t be one company collection the 20% for server costs and development but instead we would have a community run these servers themselves?&lt;br /&gt;
What if the social media flatrate would be part of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fediverse&quot;&gt;fediverse&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mastodon was quite a hype a few years ago and yet, outside of the nerd bubble, it didn’t really catch on. Nowadays servers are even closing - a common occurance in the some “host it yourself!” nerd approach. As long as it’s new and novel, it’s fun to play around with one’s own server. But after some time, maintaining a server just becomes work.&lt;br /&gt;
So what, if that social media flatrate would be part of mastodon? What if running a server would actually bring some income, depending on how many people use your server?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-social-media-flat-rate-might-create-3-solutions-at-once&quot;&gt;A social media flat rate might create 3 solutions at once&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Not having one central company controlling everything but lots instances with their own policies. So it would be suiteable for porn people as well as for “no adult content”-people - other servers having other policies. If you don’t want any porn content, use a server that doesn’t allow any porn and blocks it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Some people are really great at creating content, so they have lots of followers and get paid that way. Other people may be not that great in creating content but are very competent in managing servers, so their server runs very smooth and has lots of users. And they get paid that way - so they have an incentive to host that server not just for a few months but permanently.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It would make a platform possible without ads and without “enemy oberservation”, so maybe also a way less toxic one. And it wouldn’t create one big gatekeeper but instead lots of servers and people may choose the policy that fits them best.
Sure, it does not solve the big political conflicts. It will probably not eradicate white suprimacy, racism or sexism. But it might create another perspective on things when not the most controversial one is pushed the hardest but the one with the most support.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, that all may sound very nice. And I’d love to have the resources to make this happen. Sadly I currently don’t have them. Not the time, not energy and also not the money to buy me the time it might need to setup something like this.&lt;br /&gt;
I have lots of ideas where to start to work on a social media flat rate - e.g. talk with &lt;a href=&quot;https://eyeo.com/&quot;&gt;eyeo&lt;/a&gt; - the company owning &lt;a href=&quot;https://flattr.com/&quot;&gt;Flattr&lt;/a&gt;. I’m not sure if Flattr is the right point to start such a thing but at least talking with them would make that clear. And Flattr is already quite similar to what I have in mind.&lt;br /&gt;
Or with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.patreon.com/&quot;&gt;Patreon&lt;/a&gt;. I could imagine there could be a lot of common ground and they might be interested in developing some test case.
Or maybe with the Mastodon Community (Or their &lt;a href=&quot;https://zeonfederated.com/&quot;&gt;main developper&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;br /&gt;
Maybe it is also something one should just start developing themself. Generally I’m not convinced with creating big projects all by yourself… and my programming skills are not up for such a big thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been thinking about all of this for the past few months, but currently I need to focus on my degree (If I’m not done by next summer, I will have to invest another year on it, or never get any degree). And also need to earn money. Which lately became a bit of a hustle.&lt;br /&gt;
So I’m putting it out here and hope someone will find it and work on it. I’d be happy to help to assist with it too but, for now, I can’t realize the idea myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-do-you-think&quot;&gt;What do you think?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It could also be that the very idea of a social media flatrate is completely bogus. If so I’d be happy to hear proper arguments why the very idea is bad. Or what I missed thinking about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did talk about it with a few people and one thing came always up, so I address it here already: free in freedom does not mean free as in free beer. Yes, paying for a service a quite a burden. Payment might be a very visible barrier but is by for not the only one. Not standing the toxic culture of twitter these days is a high barrier too. People not having the energy to withstand that much toxic are practically banned from the platform. In Germany we have a public broadcaster that need to be paid by all citizens in Germany too, as creating good content is expensive.&lt;br /&gt;
There is no world without barriers. The question is what barriers we pick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am curious to see, what people may think about my idea, so please &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:gero@zweifeln.org&quot;&gt;email me&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/zweifeln/&quot;&gt;tweet at me&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
Or talk about it wherever you usually talk about these things :)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Social-Media-Flat-Rate/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Social-Media-Flat-Rate/</guid>
        
        
        <category>ideas</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Wie wird das neue Normal aussehen?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Klimawandel, Massenbrände (Amazonas, Russland, Australien), Dürren, Urwaldrodungen, Heuschreckenplagen. 
Wankende Weltmacht USA, weltweit erstarkende Demokratiefeinde, Internationale Organisationen sind schwach. (UNESCO und WHO bricht Finanzierung weg), EU praktisch unsichtbar.&lt;br /&gt;
FakeNews und Verschwörungstheorien überall, Social Bots und Klickarmeen in den sozialen Netzwerken, Journalismus ohne Geschäftsmodell.&lt;br /&gt;
Global agierende Weltkonzerne umgehen Steuern und scheffeln Milliarden.&lt;br /&gt;
Pandemie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notstandsgesetze, Versammlungsfreiheit ausgesetzt, Rausgehen nur mit triftigem Grund, Reisen aller Art bis auf weiteres Gestrichen. Sozialleben auf online begrenzt, aber Schulen, Arbeitsplätze und Shopping Malls sollen öffnen. Kassen mit Plexiglas abgetrennt, Bargeld verpönt, Prostitution und Obdachlosigkeit verboten.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ausnahmezustand. Überall Ausnahmezustand. Dabei scheint die Sonne so schön. Wollen wir in den Park?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Der Ausnahmezustand wird bleiben. Es wird sich hier und da was ändern, angepasst, korrigiert, aber grundsätzlich wird der Ausnahmezustand bleiben. Er wird normal werden.&lt;br /&gt;
Wie wird es aussehen, die neue Normal?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Was wird “wie früher” und was nicht? Die Plexiglasscheiben vor den Kassen werden bleiben. Die Dürren auch. Werden wir unsere Versammlungsfreiheit wiederbekommen? Wenn ja, wann?&lt;br /&gt;
Einer Regierung Merkel traue ich es zu, dass wir die möglichst bald wieder bekommen … aber wann wird es wieder Festivals geben?&lt;br /&gt;
Geben die Deutsche ihre Zuneigung zu Bargeld auf? Wird Prostitution wieder erlaubt werden?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welche Firmen wird es geben? Welche Fluggesellschaften? Wird es zukünftig Billigflieger geben? Bahnreisen?&lt;br /&gt;
Werden die Europäischen Grenzen wieder geöffnet? Oder wird es überall Pass- und Fieberkontrollen geben?&lt;br /&gt;
Was sind die Wirtschaftszweige der post-Corona-Zeit?&lt;br /&gt;
Wird es überhaupt eine post-Corona-Zeit geben oder wird Corona bleiben? Werden andere Pandemien kommen?&lt;br /&gt;
Welche Lebensmittel werden wir essen, wenn Dürren und Heuschrecken die Ernten vernichten?&lt;br /&gt;
Werden die Wetterkatastrophen noch schlimmer werden? Die Brände?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welche Städte werden in den Fluten versinken? Welche werden mit massiven Dämmen geschützt?&lt;br /&gt;
Wie lange werden wir noch Öl verbrennen um uns fortzubewegen oder zu heizen?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wann wird China die USA als größte Wirtschaftsmacht, wann als Weltpolizei abgelöst haben? Werden wir dann als zweite Sprache Mandarin statt Englisch lernen?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welche Medien wird es geben? Auf welche wird sich wer verlassen? Fox News wird bleiben, aber wer auf der anderen Seite?&lt;br /&gt;
Wie werden Menschen wissen können, was von Fox News kommt und was mit Journalistischer Sorgfalt geprüft? Wie wird Journalismus finanziert werden? Wo wird die Grenze zwischen Journalismus und (politischer) Werbung liegen?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ist das die Postmoderne? Alle Werte, alles bisherige hinfällig und alles wird Egoismus, Kapitalismus und postfaktisch?&lt;br /&gt;
Was für Fähigkeiten werden gebraucht werden in dieser Welt? Programmieren? BWL? Kartoffelanbau? Jagen und Sammeln? Selbstdarstellung und Schauspielerei? Rhetorik und Netzwerken? Sprachkenntnisse? Russisch, Mandarin, Spanisch?&lt;br /&gt;
Werden Dokumente mehr oder weniger wert sein? Wird der Reisepass oder das Social Media Profil wichtiger sein?  Welche Abschlüsse werden wichtig sein? Philosophie oder Medizin? Oder der Jagd- oder Führerschein?&lt;br /&gt;
Wird es Ausweise geben für “Fox News Anhänger”? Oder Google Mitarbeiter*in?&lt;br /&gt;
Wo und wie lange wird der Rechtsstaat sich halten? Wer wird ihn garantieren?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Die Institutionen werden nicht verschwinden, aber werden sie noch entscheiden? Können? Wenn ja, was?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wir leben in ungewöhnlichen Zeiten. Wie früher wird es nicht wieder werden. Aber wie wird das neue “Normal” aussehen?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Wie-wird-das-neue-Normal-aussehen/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Wie-wird-das-neue-Normal-aussehen/</guid>
        
        
        <category>politics</category>
        
        <category>ideas</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Who am I?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m a queer sex worker. So, there is it. I’m out. Can I go now?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, I can’t, because that is not, how outings works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned that already years ago, when I outed myself as gay. It’s not a one-time thing. You may come out to your parents or friends … but that does not make your colleagues know about it. Or your distant relatives. Or your neighbours. Or the parents of your kids friends.
Outing is a continuing process. And a painful one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hate the need of outing myself. But apparently whatever society might see as abnormal, as strange, as &lt;em&gt;queer&lt;/em&gt;, is something people have to publicly admit. To stand up for. To explain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hate it. I hate that I have to explain myself for being. That I have to explain my existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every time you’re outing yourself to a friend, a family member, a neighbour, a colleague, you’re risking rejection. It creates a shitload of questions in your mind to work through. &lt;em&gt;When&lt;/em&gt; do you out yourself? To &lt;em&gt;whom&lt;/em&gt;? &lt;em&gt;How&lt;/em&gt;? &lt;em&gt;What reaction&lt;/em&gt; may you get? How to deal with whatever reaction it might create?&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Who to not out to&lt;/em&gt; because you do not want to get the imagined reaction?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything sexual is still a topic that many people feel very uncomfortable talking about. So when you finally take your guts and out yourself to someone, it might be that the fact that your LGBTIQ+ or a sex worker is no reason for rejection but the very fact that you’re “pushing that topic” onto them might cause rejection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it is not only the question if how someone might react to the outing itself but also to the urge of talking about it at all. The “we don’t talk about that topic” reaction is quite common.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I kinda get it. Everything sexual is still a big topic to never talk about in society. (Similar to mental health issues. Admitting mental health issues is actually quite an outing too.)&lt;br /&gt;
And I’m &lt;em&gt;kinda&lt;/em&gt; okay with it. If someone does not want to talk about a topic I don’t want to force it onto them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, because these topics are so deep in the “do not speak about it” land, you cannot really talk about it, without outing yourself. If you want to talk about gay sex as a man, everyone will know, you’re at least questioning your heterosexuality. And it’s quite the same with sex work. If you want to talk about the actual lives of sex workers, everyone around you will believe, you’re either a sex worker or a client. (Or an old-fashioned feminist working in the rescue industry, not giving any agency to sex workers but believe you have to speak for them, as they are all enslaved and brainwashed so they can’t speak for themselves.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you out yourself to someone and they are neither rejection you for the thing you’re outing yourself for nor for the fact that you find it okay to talk about it, it mostly results in tons and tons of questions.
As much as I love curiosity and the interest in my life, it very easily becomes the sole topic to talk about. When I’m outing myself in a group of people it either makes no-one talking to me any more because they don’t know how to talk about it and feel very uncomfortable talking about it - or (worse) they feel uncomfortable talking to &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; because you just became a persona non grata.&lt;br /&gt;
Or you have all the attention and whatever the topic was before the outing, will be gone because everyone is so much more interested in you. Not actually in you but in your sex life. If the topic in the group was taxes and I had a question about doing taxes as a self employed sex worker, I most likely will not even get an answer to my actual question but will be asked 437 questions about evil, nice, ugly, fat, old, skinny, young, handsome, rich or poor clients; about the legal situation of sex work, how I work, when, where, what sex practices are my favourites, how to have anal sex without shitting the other one and if I want sex without payment. (No, I do not.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again: I appreciate curiosity and interest in my work. Society knowing more about sex and sex work would be incredible helpful. But answering the same questions over and over again can become very draining. Sometimes I think about starting to charge for answering these questions. It can provide answers to questions - in many professions that is in itself a business model.&lt;br /&gt;
On the other hand, there are people aware of the annoyance of having outed yourself and being asked &lt;em&gt;ALL&lt;/em&gt; the questions and therefore avoid asking me about it at all, as they don’t want to annoy me - and then often quietly forming opinions about my work. And at least with friends, that is even worse to me: friends avoiding a topic they have questions about but instead of asking me, they are googling stuff and just assume something. So, if you we are close and you have questions about me doing sex work, please ask me! I’m actually way happier to answer a question I have been asked hundreds of times before, than learning, you assuming stuff about me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Outing yourself as LGBTIQ will very easily be the one thing that identifies you. “Who are you talking about?” - “The gay guy!” - “Ahh! I see …”&lt;br /&gt;
It’s the same with outing yourself as a sex worker. “Who are you talking about?” - “The hooker”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I understand that people identify someone by whatever makes someone singular in a group. If there is only one guy with long hair at a party, that guy will be most likely referred to as the “long haired guy”. That way of identifying people however can become hurtful as it quietly reduces your whole existence to that one thing.  You’re the hooker now. Being also a maths genius or artist becomes at best secondary if not completely erased.
But if you don’t out yourself, you’re constantly living a double life. You have experiences in one part of your life that you can’t share to the other one. That can create a lot of mental load and stress to keep everything to yourself or have at best a few people to talk about - and always have another story in mind on what to tell people about your life, that makes sense to them but is far enough from their lives so you don’t get trapped in your own stories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a sex worker outing is quite bi-directional. It’s not just the question if/how to talk to your friends and family about your sex worker life - but also about what to tell clients about your private life. Most sex workers work under different names. Often for security reasons.&lt;br /&gt;
I work under a different name too and notices it’s for me not only about security but also about keeping work and private stuff apart. I have very intimate moments with clients and yet, that is professional for me. Similar to therapists knowing very personal stuff about their clients, they still won’t become friends. Or teachers using different names on their facebook profile so their students won’t find their facebook profiles. Clients can be very nice but they are still clients and I need them to stay out of my private life. I noticed a lot of them are quite interested in my private life and telling something about me makes them often more comfortable to open up about themselves and gives them a better session. So I gave my work persona quite a private life too - but it isn’t really mine. It’s an easier, nicer, less complicated one, so I can make them feel intimate with me and still it on a professional level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have some acting experience and noticed it helps me a lot in sex work to switch into my work persona - and leaves my private trouble behind for that time. And after a session I’m switching back to my private me, leaving the session behind. So over time I developed a proper work character.&lt;br /&gt;
And to be clear: I’m not doing that, because I don’t like my clients or I have to become someone else to “endure” a session or something. My sessions are okay. My work is quite okay.&lt;br /&gt;
It is my way of keeping professional and private stuff seperated and give my clients their fantasies and “boyfriend experience”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However over time there evolves a grey area in between. What is with political activism or sex work colleagues? If I’m getting interviewed about sex work, am I doing it under my sex work name and try to steer people to my sex work persona as it might bring new clients, or am I doing it under my legal name, not being able to gain new clients for the job that currently pays my bills?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is with everything publicly? Social media? What about acting or modelling? What name do I want to push publicly and what if someone knowing me by one name now reads learns about the other one?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can I use pictures I use professionally also on some personal, non sex work social media? (No, I can’t, due to Google images reverse search. It’s gonna become interesting and quite scary when face recognition software becomes available to more people)&lt;br /&gt;
Should I eradicate my “private” me on the Internet and only act as my sex work persona on the Internet? (There are very few brothels/studios for male sex workers … so it is necessary to find your clients online. So having your sex work identity only offline does not work - it needs to be online too)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes I feel like Eli Cohen in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Spy_(TV_series)&quot;&gt;“The Spy”&lt;/a&gt; - slowly blurring the lines between his two caracters. In the last episode he says: “Those nightmares she’s talking about, they’re not even mine, they are Kamel’s [his spy identity]. Taking off my clothes, it doesn’t work anymore. I can’t put him away. I’m pretending to be me.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel quite the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can become someone else, you can impersonate someone for some time - but you cannot unlearn that person. You cannot unlearn you acting role. You cannot not know your work identity in private. That is how not outing yourself to family or friends, makes you behave professionally even in private. How you’re setting up an act for friends?! Can they still be friends, when you’re setting up an act for them? When you can’t be yourself around your friends?!&lt;br /&gt;
I guess that is the reason I’m writing this blog post on my private blog. I want to be out. I want my friends to know about that other life I have. I cannot act professionally in my work and private life. Whatever “private life” actually means on a public blog on the Internet. Maybe I should shut it down. Maybe I should use social media only as my sex work persona … but then, what will my private life still be? What will be left “private” for me with little to no family?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I am again thinking over and over and over again what to do. Doubting so much about my life, not knowing what to do. “Zweifeln”. The Identity I gave myself 8 years ago. It seems still a precise description of being me.&lt;br /&gt;
I want to be me. The whole me, the queer sex worker me but also the actor, the artist, the moderator, the photographer, the philosophy and culture student, the digital politics and activist me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;There is no comment section here. If you have questions or comments, please write me an e-mail: &lt;strong&gt;gero [at] zweifeln.org&lt;/strong&gt; - or mention me on twitter: &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/zweifeln&quot;&gt;@zweifeln&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jan 2020 00:56:14 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/who-am-I/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/who-am-I/</guid>
        
        
        <category>personal</category>
        
        <category>politics</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Selbsthilfegruppe Prokrastination</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Ich habe ein Prokrastinationsproblem.
Einiges bekomme ich in meinem Leben ganz gut auf die Reihe und ein paar Dinge fallen mir super schwer und ich schiebe sie Monate und Jahre vor mir her. “Einfach machen” funktioniert “einfach” nicht und ich glaube, ich habe verstanden, warum und habe eine Idee, wie die Hilfe/Struktur aussehen könnte/sollte, damit ich die ewig prokrastinierten Projekte doch noch hin bekomme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Projekte, die ich nicht prokrastiniere, sind Projekte mit mehr sozialer Kontrolle. Egal, ob &lt;em&gt;wirklich&lt;/em&gt; feste und externe Deadlines (feste Prüfungstermine) durch Dritte oder das Projekte, die ich nicht alleine, sondern im Team bearbeite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ich habe immer wieder versucht die festen Deadlines zu erzwingen, aber wenn &lt;em&gt;ich&lt;/em&gt; die Deadlines setze, sind sie nicht fest genug. Ich weiß ja, dass es meine selbstgesetzten Deadlines sind - und es eigentlich nur mich interessiert, ob ich die einhalte, oder nicht.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zeitweise habe ich Coworking Spaces gearbeitet, in der Hoffnung, dass mir das genug sozialen Kontrolle/Druck gibt, mich um meine eigenen, prokrastinierten Projekte zu kümmern. Coworking Spaces machen mich teils sehr produktiv, aber das vor allem für Projekte, in denen auch andere Menschen involviert sind. Sie verstärken meine Prokrastination gewissermaßen sogar. Noch mehr an anderen Projekten arbeiten, um sich nicht mit den eigenen Projekten auseinandersetzen zu müssen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Was ich also brauche, ist nicht Menschen um mich herum beim Arbeiten, sondern Menschen, die an meinen Projekten interessiert sind. Ich brauche Menschen, die meinen Fortschritt kontrollieren. Mit denen ich regelmäßig bespreche, wie ich voran komme - oder wenn ich nicht voran komme, warum ich das nicht tue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ich bin mir ziemlich sicher, dass ich nicht der einzige Mensch bin, der aus eben jenem Grund prokrastiniert; dem die soziale Kontrolle fehlt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wenn es davon aber mehrere gibt … warum tun wir uns dann nicht zusammen und bilden eine Gruppe, die sich gegenseitig - freundlich - kontrolliert?
Die sich jede Woche trifft und der restlichen Gruppe erzählt, wie das vormals prokrastinierte Projekt so voran geht?
Eine Selbsthilfegruppe für Prokrastinateur*innen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Genau das möchte ich anbieten. Ein wöchentliches Treffen zur Projektbesprechung - ähnlich einer Teambesprechung. Nur, dass es nicht um ein Projekt geht, dass das gesamte Team gemeinsam angeht, sondern um viele eigene Projekte, die trotzdem besprochen werden können - und vielleicht auch sollten, damit sie voran kommen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wenn es einige Leute in Berlin gibt, die daran Interesse haben, lasst uns gerne ein wöchentliches Treffen in Berlin haben, wenn interessierte irgendwo auf der Welt sind, gerne auch per Videokonferenz.
Offline Meetings sind oft effizienter als Videokonferenzen, aber auch Videokonferenzen funktionieren ganz okay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;wer-hat-interesse-an-einer-prokrastinations-selbsthilfegruppe&quot;&gt;Wer hat Interesse an einer Prokrastinations-Selbsthilfegruppe?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schreibt mir: &lt;strong&gt;gero [at] zweifeln.org&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In der Mail wäre eine kurze Vorstellung schön, wer ihr seid und was eurer Projekt ist, dass ihr prokrastiniert - und wann euch ein solches Treffen gut passen würde: eher vormittags, eher nachmittags, eher abends - und wenn es einen präferierten Wochentag gibt, auch gerne den.
(Daraus baue ich dann ein Doodle zur genaueren Terminfindung.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mein Projekt ist mein Fernstudium … dem seit Jahren ein paar Hausarbeiten und die Bachelorarbeit fehlt. Und wenn das geschafft ist, gibt es noch ein Buchprojekt, eine Politkampagne, ein Filmprojekt und ein Homeserver-Projekt … aber zuerst das Fernstudium beenden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;update-2020-01-14&quot;&gt;Update 2020-01-14&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nach einigen Rückmeldungen wurde mir klar, dass ich besser erklären muss, was eigentlich meine Idee dieses wöchentlichen Treffens ist - und vor allem, was es nicht ist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ich bin kein Psychotherapeut und traue mir nicht zu, eine Gruppentherapie zu leiten. Ich will auch keine Gruppentherapie. Ich will keine Runde, in der wir &lt;em&gt;über&lt;/em&gt; Prokrastination reden.
Ich will eine Runde, in der wir über die Projekte reden, die wir prokrastinieren.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ich will den Fokus auf den Projekten, die wir alle vor uns her schieben. Ich will nicht wöchentlich abstrakte Gespräche über “Prokrastination” und Tipps, wie abstrakt weniger prokrastiniert werden kann, sondern konkret über einzelne Vorhaben reden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ich will, dass wir uns gegenseitig Hausaufgaben zu unseren Vorhaben geben - und damit selbst für Struktur sorgen, die wir brauchen, um unsere Vorhaben umzusetzen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_left&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/images/posts/Studentensyndrom.png&quot; alt=&quot;Schema Arbeitsentwicklung von Prokrastination&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Ich will von dieser aus der &lt;a href=&quot;https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prokrastination&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt; kopierten Darstellung …
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img_left&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/images/posts/Selbsthilfegruppe Prokrastination.png&quot; alt=&quot;Schema Arbeitsentwickling, wie ich sie mir mit dieser Selbsthilfegruppe wünsche&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	… zu dieser selbstgebauten.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Denn insbesondere bei Vorhaben, die (noch) keinen festen Endtermin haben, fehlt auch die “Oh jetzt wird’s knapp!” Entwicklung … und die Vorhaben dümpeln nur so vor sich hin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Es geht mir darum, wöchentliche, “kleine Deadlines” zu haben. Und ich lernte, dass die für mich nur funktionieren, wenn es auch Menschen gibt, die kontrollieren, dass ich sie einhalte.
Im Gegenzug biete ich an, eben jene “kleine Deadlines” für andere Menschen zu kontrollieren.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Und weil wir dauernd kleine Deadlines brauchen: &lt;strong&gt;wer mitmachen möchte, möge bis spätestens Freitag, 17.01.2020, 14.00 Uhr&lt;/strong&gt;  eine Mail an &lt;strong&gt;gero [at] zweifeln.org&lt;/strong&gt; schreiben. Und dann gucke ich, wie viele wir sind und wann/wie wir uns treffen können und wie es weiter geht.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/Selbsthilfegruppe-Prokrastination/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/Selbsthilfegruppe-Prokrastination/</guid>
        
        
        <category>moderation</category>
        
        <category>personal</category>
        
        <category>ideas</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Soziale Infrastruktur in Ostdeutschland</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Bei den Landtagswahlen in Sachsen und Brandenburg hat die AfD Rekordergebnisse erzielt. Warum aber werden die Nazis in den Ostdeutschen Bundesländern gewählt?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Da gibt es mehrere valide Erklärungsansätze, die allesamt nicht rechtfertigen, Nazis zu wählen. Aber ich glaube, es hilft, sich die Lage etwas detaillierter anzusehen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;infrastruktur&quot;&gt;Infrastruktur&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wer sich die Ergebnisse der Europawahl im Mai genau anschaut, sieht, dass die AfD nicht perse in Ostdeutschland stärker ist als in Westdeutschland (so hat sie mehr Prozente in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bundeswahlleiter.de/europawahlen/2019/ergebnisse/bund-99/land-5/kreis-5513.html&quot;&gt;Gelsenkirchen&lt;/a&gt; als in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bundeswahlleiter.de/europawahlen/2019/ergebnisse/bund-99/land-12/kreis-12054.html&quot;&gt;Potsdam&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bundeswahlleiter.de/europawahlen/2019/ergebnisse/bund-99/land-16/kreis-16053.html&quot;&gt;Jena&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bundeswahlleiter.de/europawahlen/2019/ergebnisse/bund-99/land-14/kreis-14713.html&quot;&gt;Leipzig&lt;/a&gt; oder &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bundeswahlleiter.de/europawahlen/2019/ergebnisse/bund-99/land-13/kreis-13003.html&quot;&gt;Rostock&lt;/a&gt; bekommen).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Die AfD ist nicht perse in Ostdeutschland stärker als in Westdeutschland, sondern vor allem in strukturschwachen Regionen stark - und das sind vor allem die ländlichen Regionen in Ostdeutschland.
Strukturschwach bedeutet aber auch nicht perse ländlich. Gelsenkirchen ist ja selbst eine Großstadt. Sie hat wie viele Städte im Ruhrgebiet mit hohen Arbeitslosenzahlen und dem Rückgang der Bergbau-Industrie zu kämpfen. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.handelsblatt.com/politik/deutschland/zukunftsatlas-2019/&quot;&gt;Der “Zukunftsatlas” sieht Gelsenkirchen auf den Platz 371 von 401 Landkreisen in Deutschland. (Das ist der 3. schlechteste in Westdeutschland)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Westdeutschland ist im Schnitt stärker besiedelt als Ostdeutschland, was u.a. Infrastruktur leichter finanzierbar macht. (Je mehr Menschen mit einem Zug fahren, je einfacher sind die Betriebskosten gedeckt.) Und die ländlichen Räume in Westdeutschland sind stärker suburbanisiert als in Ostdeutschland. Daher ist der Mangel an Infrastruktur in Westdeutschland häufig weniger tragisch als in Ostdeutschland - die Menschen kommen einfacher in Gegenden mit besserer Infrastruktur.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Selbst Großstädte wie Chemnitz, Dresden oder Magdeburg, in denen die AfD starke Ergebnisse hat, sind beeindruckend abgeschnitten. &lt;a href=&quot;https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Liste_der_Intercity-Express-Linien#Aktuelle_Linien_(2018/19)&quot;&gt;Nach Chemnitz oder Magdeburg fährt kein ICE, nach Dresden nur einer&lt;/a&gt;. Auffallend dabei ist auch: die AfD hat im Umland dieser Städte durchweg noch mehr Stimmen bekommen, als in den Städten selbst.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mit dem Fall der Mauer und dem Zusammenbruch der DDR sind weite Teile der Wirtschaft zum Erliegen gekommen. Millionen Menschen innerhalb kurzer Zeit in den Westen gezogen. Dort gab es Arbeit.
Gut aufgearbeitet hat dieses Phänomen &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zeit.de/politik/deutschland/2019-05/ost-west-wanderung-abwanderung-ostdeutschland-umzug&quot;&gt;Zeit Online&lt;/a&gt;.
Besonders tragisch: es sind vor allem die Jungen, gut Ausgebildeten, die wegziehen. Es bleiben vor allem Alte. Vor der Wende war der Altersdurchschnitt im Osten niedriger als im Westen. Heute ist es andersherum.
Die &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mdr.de/nachrichten/vermischtes/abwanderung-gestoppt-mehr-westdeutsche-ziehen-nach-osten-100.html&quot;&gt;“Trendwende”, dass inzwischen mehr Menschen aus Westdeutschland nach Ostdeutschland ziehen&lt;/a&gt;, beruht vor allem darauf, dass ein paar Großstädte im Osten (&lt;a href=&quot;https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leipzig#Einwohnerentwicklung&quot;&gt;Leipzig&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rostock#Einwohnerentwicklung&quot;&gt;Rostock&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jena#Bev%C3%B6lkerungsentwicklung&quot;&gt;Jena&lt;/a&gt;) und der Speckgürtel von Berlin wächst (&lt;a href=&quot;https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Falkensee#Bev%C3%B6lkerungsentwicklung&quot;&gt;Falkensee&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oranienburg#Bev%C3%B6lkerungsentwicklung&quot;&gt;Oranienburg&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bev%C3%B6lkerungsentwicklung_von_Bernau_bei_Berlin#Bev%C3%B6lkerung_ab_2001&quot;&gt;Bernau&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;jugend&quot;&gt;Jugend&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mit den jungen Menschen gingen und gehen immer noch diejenigen, die primär das Sozialleben ausmachen. Diejenigen, die Feste organisieren und feiern, die Vereine aufbauen und sich darin engagieren. Diejenigen, die sich eher mit Kunst und Kultur beschäftigen. Vor allem diejenigen, die sich mit Neuem beschäftigen, mit Globalisierung, Digitalisierung und der Klimakrise. Diejenigen, die potentiell eher neue Unternehmen aufbauen. Diese Bevölkerungsschicht fehlt auf dem Land und “überlässt” damit gewissermaßen das Land den Gestrigen. Klassischer &lt;a href=&quot;https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talentabwanderung&quot;&gt;Braindrain&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.spiegel.de/politik/deutschland/ergebnisse-sachsen-wahl-afd-punktet-bei-den-jungen-a-1284494.html&quot;&gt;Das gerade die jungen Menschen in Sachsen die AfD wählen, überrascht mich wenig.&lt;/a&gt;. Die meisten jungen Menschen gehen weg, sobald sie können. Die, die bleiben, tun es oft aus Überzeugung.
Der Weggang der jungen Menschen liegt zum Teil an mangelnder Infrastruktur und fehlenden guten Arbeitsplätzen. Oft aber ist es inzwischen auch Flucht. Flucht vor den Nazis, vor Übergriffen, Mobbing und Hetzjagden. Flucht, weil die Breite der Gesellschaft LGBTIQ-Menschen, Menschen anderer Hautfarbe oder auch nur andersdenkender Menschen nicht vor Nazis schützt.
Es sind nicht alle Menschen in Ostdeutschland Nazis, aber wenn es Nazi-Übergriffe gibt, wird sich oft weg geduckt und weg geguckt. Bloß nicht selbst ins Visier der Nazis gelangen.
Vielleicht sogar besser noch mitmachen, dann ist man vor den Nazis sicher. “Was ist schon dabei ein Flüchtlingsheim anzugreifen? Die Polizei macht eh nichts, bei den Nazis bin ich sicher.”
Möchtegern-Mitläufer, die sich in ihrer Radikalität gegenseitig überbieten und damit selbst zu Nazi-Anführern werden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;gesellschaftsleben&quot;&gt;Gesellschaftsleben&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In der DDR wurde die Kirche bekämpft. Ostdeutschland ist noch heute das atheistischste Gebiet Europas (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.norc.org/NewsEventsPublications/PressReleases/Pages/international-perspectives-on-theism.aspx&quot;&gt;sagt eine Studie der NORC Organisation der Uni Chicago&lt;/a&gt;. Religion ist für viele Menschen ein Anker. Eine Gebilde, die in grundlegenden Lebensfragen Antworten gibt.
In der DDR wurde diese Aufgabe von Partei, FDJ und den Gewerkschaften übernommen. Seit dem Zusammenfall der DDR klafft hier eine große Lücke.
Eine Lücke, die rechtsradikale gerne für sich nutzen. 
Mitte der 2000er gab es viel Aufregung um die &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.faz.net/aktuell/politik/inland/npd-kampf-um-die-jungen-leute-1209817.html&quot;&gt;Schulhof-CDs der NPD - und deren Jugendarbeit&lt;/a&gt;. Gruppierungen wie diese gehen gezielt in die Lücken und bieten ein Sozialleben, das junge Menschen in Ostdeutschland sonst nicht bekommen. 
Was in Westdeutschland die Pfadfinder sind, erfüllen in Ostdeutschland oft rechtsradikale Kameradschaften. Sie gehen gezielt in Sportvereine und indoktrinieren Kinder und Jugendliche:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;de&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Ich habe in meiner Jugend in Sachsen-Anhalt erlebt, wie Neonazis vor allem über Fußballvereine die Wähler schon im Kinderalter rekrutiert haben. Da kam der Coach vor den Kommunalwahlen in die Kabine und sagte „Jungs, am Sonntag bitte die NPD wählen“.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Shahak Shapira (@ShahakShapira) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ShahakShapira/status/1132928624884109313?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;May 27, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Es gibt in Ostdeutschland keine Volksparteien. Die gab es seit der Wende auch nie. Die CDU hat in Sachsen-Anhalt etwa 6600 Mitglieder. Die SPD etwa 3600. Das sind nicht mal 2 Mitglieder auf 1000 Menschen. Selbst die Linkspartei hat nur marginal mehr Mitglieder als die SPD.
Hingegen hat die AfD in ihrer erst kurzen Existenz schon über 1000 Mitglieder und wächst beeindruckend schnell (während die anderen Parteien eher stagnieren, wenn nicht sogar Mitglieder verlieren). &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mz-web.de/sachsen-anhalt/landespolitik/mitgliederzahlen-afd-und-gruene-legen-kraeftig-zu---cdu-und-linke-verlieren-31944380&quot;&gt;Quelle&lt;/a&gt;
Damit fehlt ein wichtiges, erklärendes und zuhörendes Bindeglied zwischen den Entscheidungsträger*innen und der Bevölkerung. Es gibt quasi keinerlei Ortsverbände der Parteien auf dem Land. Die Politik findet “da oben” statt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;eliten&quot;&gt;Eliten&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Die Eliten Deutschlands sind westdeutsch. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zeit.de/2017/46/ost-quote-fuehrungspositionen/komplettansicht&quot;&gt;Auch die Eliten Ostdeutschlands sind westdeutsch&lt;/a&gt; (und weiß, männlich, cis und heterosexuell).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Es gibt keine überregional bedeutenden Medien in Ostdeutschland - das führt zu einer distanzierten Berichterstattung über Ostdeutschland. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zeit.de/politik/deutschland/2019-08/ostdeutschland-westdeutschland-medien-presse-berichterstattung-osten/komplettansicht&quot;&gt;Johannes Hilje hat gut beschrieben, wie dieses Problem der AfD hilft&lt;/a&gt;.
Und selbst die regional bedeutendsten Zeitungen gehören in fast ganz Ostdeutschland alleine &lt;a href=&quot;https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Verlagsgesellschaft_Madsack#Tageszeitungen&quot;&gt;dem MADSACK Verlag&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wenn der Spiegel eine Woche vor der Wahl mit maximaler Arroganz alle Ostdeutschen zu Pegida macht, hilft das auch nur dem “Lügenpresse”-Gerede der AfD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-partner=&quot;tweetdeck&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;de&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Guten Abend! Der neue SPIEGEL ist da. Digital ab sofort hier, morgen überall am Kiosk: &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/vWJ4tFD94F&quot;&gt;https://t.co/vWJ4tFD94F&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/gmj2xHdMXG&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/gmj2xHdMXG&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; DER SPIEGEL (@DerSPIEGEL) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/DerSPIEGEL/status/1164930310280269824?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;August 23, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Westdeutschland gibt es ein politisch-gesellschaftliches Zugehörigkeitsgefühl. Es gibt Verbindung zu politischen Parteien, zu Religionsgemeinschaften, zu Stiftungen und Vereinen, zu Unternehmen, bundesweit relevanten Medien und wichtigen Forschungseinrichtungen.
Wer ein Anliegen hat, findet im erweiterten Bekanntenkreis irgendwen mit Einfluss - egal ob in Medien, Wirtschaft oder Politik.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Ostdeutschalnd ist dieses Zugehörigkeitsgefühl deutlich schwächer ausgeprägt. Es gibt nicht nur weniger gesellschaftliche Institutionen in Ostdeutschland, sondern auch die Entscheidungen werden seltener von Menschen aus der Region getroffen. Es erzeugt ein Gefühl eher verwaltet zu werden, als selbst agieren zu können.
Dazu hat auch die &lt;a href=&quot;https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Treuhandanstalt&quot;&gt;Treuhandanstalt&lt;/a&gt; entschieden beigetragen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Michael Seemann (@mspro) hat vor 2,5 Jahren &lt;a href=&quot;http://mspr0.de/?p=4696&quot;&gt;eine neue Elite - die “globalen Klasse” - beschrieben&lt;/a&gt;.
Diese Elite, diese Informationsarbeiter*innen sind es, die in Ostdeutschland kaum vorkommen. Das Internet ist langsam, die Bahnen kommen selten, die letzte Kneipe im Ort hat zu gemacht.
Die moderne Elite kann dort nicht arbeiten, nicht leben. Sie ist für die Menschen in Ostdeutschland nicht erreichbar - und andersherum. Diese Elite hat auch keinen Bezug zu Ostdeutschland. “Durchfahrland” - da, wo der ICE nicht hält.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Es geht nicht darum, dass die Menschen in Ostdeutschland perse kein Geld haben (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fr.de/wirtschaft/aktienbesitzer-sind-allem-westdeutsche-10958837.html&quot;&gt;auch wenn Westdeutsche im Schnitt deutlich reicher sind als Ostdeutsche&lt;/a&gt;), sondern darum, dass Ostdeutschland tatsächlich in Teilen vom öffentlichen Leben der liberalen, progressiven, pluralistischen Gesellschaft abgeschnitten ist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;identität-und-geschichte&quot;&gt;Identität und Geschichte&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Es gibt nicht &lt;em&gt;die&lt;/em&gt; Ostdeutsche Identität. Die DDR existierte 39 Jahre, die gut bewachte Grenze (inklusive der Berliner Mauer) 28 Jahre.
Diese Zeit hat Menschen in Ostdeutschland geprägt. Aber sie ist zu kurz, um eine umfassende spezifisch Ostdeutsche Identität zu prägen. Es gibt einige Dinge, die in Ostdeutschland anders laufen, als in Westdeutschland. Aber nicht alles, was heute als “Ostdeutsch” gilt, wurde in der DDR geschaffen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newstatesman.com/world/europe/2017/09/what-britain-needs-understand-about-profound-and-ancient-divisions-germany&quot;&gt;diesem NewStatesman Artikel&lt;/a&gt; wird beschrieben, dass Konrad Adenauer 1955 überlegte Westberlin gegen Thüringen zu tauschen, denn die NSDAP bekamen schon seiner Zeit mehr Zustimmung im Osten als im Westen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sachsen war ein Schlüsselgebiet der NSDAP. Hier gab es den ersten GAU außerhalb Bayerns und deutlich überdurchschnittlich viele NSDAP-Mitglieder, wie auch deutlich überdurchschnittlich viele Menschen in angeschlossenen nationalsozialistischen Verbände.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Das widerum ist historisch auch nicht so verwunderlich. Der letzte König Sachsens - Friedrich August III - war außerordentlich beliebt. Als er 1918 auf seinen Thron verzichtete, sei die Mehrheit der Bevölkerung dagegen gewesen, schreibt der Chemnitzer Geschichtsprofessor Frank-Lothar Kroll.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Friedrich_August_III._(Sachsen)#Tod_und_Beisetzung&quot;&gt;1932 kamen 500.000(!) Menschen zur Bestattungszeremonie des letzten sächsischen Königs nach Dresden&lt;/a&gt;. Das sind mehr, als seinerzeit in Dresden überhaupt gelebt haben.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frank Richter, langjähriger Chef des sächsischen Zentrums für politische Bildung, schreibt in seinem Buch, dass 1989 in Dresden nicht nur Deutschland, sondern auch weiß-grüne Sachsenflaggen geschwungen wurden, teils mit königlichem Wappen - obwohl das Land Sachsen in der 1952 in der DDR aufgelöst wurde.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sachsen wurde als Kurfürstentum und Königreich über Jahrhunderte durchgehend von Monarchen regiert. Es gab einen umfassenden Hofstaat und empfand Sachsen waren Stolz darauf, ein eigenes Königshaus zu haben.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Der Schritt von der Verehrung der Monarchie als bester Staatsform zum Nationalsozialismus mit starken Führern ist klein.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Die DDR hat über die Themen Rassismus, Antisemitismus und Neonazis ausgiebig geschwiegen, denn worüber offiziell nicht geredet wird, das existiert auch nicht.
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hagalil.com/2019/05/antisemitismus-ddr/&quot;&gt;Harry Waible hat akkribisch herausgearbeitet, das es in der DDR durchaus Rassismus, Antisemitismus und viele Neonazis gab.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wenn Rassismus, Antisemitismus und Fremdenfeindlichkeit nicht angesprochen wird, können diese Probleme auch nicht bearbeitet werden.
Das ist, warum &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lvz.de/Region/Mitteldeutschland/Biedenkopf-Ostdeutsche-weitgehend-immun-gegen-Rechtsradikalismus&quot;&gt;Kurt Biedenkopfs “Ostdeutsche sind immun gegen Rechtsradikalismus”&lt;/a&gt; so verheerend ist. Natürlich sind nicht alle Ostdeutschen Nazis. Es wählen ja nicht alle die AfD - sondern nur 1/4 der Wählenden. Wenn die Nichtwähler*innen dazu genommen werden, sind es nur noch so 1/6.
Und auch nicht alle AfD-Wähler*innen sind Nazis. Sehr wohl aber haben alle Menschen, die die AfD wählen, kein Problem mit Nazis.
Und das widerum ist ein massives Problem. Es geht ja nicht nur darum, ob alles Nazis sind, sonder auch darum, wer die Nazis unterstützt. Und wenn ein 1/6 der gesamten Bevölkerung die Nazis der AfD in Parlamente wählt ist das eine Katastrophe.
Die Nazis brauchen nicht die Unterstützung der gesamten Bevölkerung. (Einen Teil davon wollen sie ja eh auslöschen). Es reicht, wenn es niemanden mehr gibt, der sich traut den Nazis in den Weg zu stellen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ich kann Gedankengänge einiger AfD-Wählenden nachvollziehen, die argumentieren, dass sie selbst kein Problem mit der AfD haben. In Ostdeutschland leben prozentual weniger Menschen mit Migrationshintergrund. Es wird schnell ein “mir doch egal, ob die gegen Ausländer hetzen”, weil niemand selbst betroffen ist. Und auch viele nicht bewusst Menschen mit Migrationshintergrund kennen. Sie wiegen in Sicherheit vor den Nazis und wollen mit der Wahl der AfD “der Politik einen Denkzettel verpassen”.
Diese - sehr egoistische, aber in sich schlüssige - Argumentation, ist eine politische Bankrotterklärung. Menschen, die derart egoistisch argumentieren, wollen keine Demokratie. Sie wollen keine plurale Gesellschaft, keine politischen Diskussionen. sie wollen das starke Führer für Ruhe sorgen. Sie wollen &lt;a href=&quot;https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_befreite_Zone&quot;&gt;national befreite Zonen&lt;/a&gt; und Naziregierung.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;und-jetzt&quot;&gt;Und jetzt?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Wehret den Anfängen!” ist zu spät. Es hat schon längst begonnen.
Wir können Demokratietheorie-Debatten führen und weiter analysieren, wie die wenige (soziale) Infrastruktur in Ostdeutschland oft von Nazis beherrscht oder zumindest die Nazis darin toleriert werden. Aber die Analysen alleine machen noch nichts. Die produzieren nur bedrucktes Papier.
Wie es wenig pluralistische Öffentlichkeit in Ostdeutschland gibt, ist ja eigentlich auch allen klar. Und ohne Öffentlichkeit, entsteht keine Demokratie, das ist auch keine neue Erkenntnis.
Öffentlichkeit lässt sich nicht von außen erzwingen. Es bringt nichts, wenn die FAZ oder der Spiegel mehr “über den Osten” berichten. Das können die Menschen in Ostdeutschland nur selbst. Demokratie muss aus sich selbst heraus wachsen. Die Initiativen, die es gibt, können aber sehr wohl unterstützt werden.
Sowohl die demokratischen politischen Parteien, wie auch zivilgesellschaftliches Engagement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wir müssen aufhören, die AfD als “bürgerlich” oder “konservativ” zu bezeichnen und ihrer Nazi-Propaganda damit weiterer Nahrung geben. Stattdessen sollten wir über Naziterror reden - insbesondere in Ostdeutschland und Sachsen.
Und Nazis bekämpfen mit allen Mitteln, die die Demokratie gerade noch erlaubt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wir brauchen massiv mehr soziale Infrastruktur mit klarer Kante gegen Nazis. Wir brauchen Zufluchtsorte, die vor Nazis sicher sind, in denen Demokratie sicher ist und wachsen kann.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bücherquellen&quot;&gt;Bücherquellen:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Günther Heydemann, Jan Erik Schulte, Francesca Weil (Hg.): “Sachsen und der Nationalsizialismus”, Vadenhoeck &amp;amp; Ruprech, Göttingen 2014 S. 45 (Auswertung der Parteistatistiken der NSDAP von 1935) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Frank-Lothar Kroll: &lt;em&gt;die Herrscher Sachsens&lt;/em&gt;, München: C. H. Beck 2004, S. 306ff. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Frank-Lothar Kroll: &lt;em&gt;die Herrscher Sachsens&lt;/em&gt;, München: C. H. Beck 2004, S. 318 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Frank Richter: &lt;em&gt;Gehört Sachsen noch zu Deutschland?&lt;/em&gt;, Berlin: Ullstein 2019, S. 67 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 02 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2019/Soziale-Infrastruktur-in-Ostdeutschland/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2019/Soziale-Infrastruktur-in-Ostdeutschland/</guid>
        
        
        <category>politics</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Copyright Riotcop</title>
        <description>&lt;div class=&quot;img_right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/crrc.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Photo: Konstanze Burkhart
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday I went to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://berlingegen13.wordpress.com/&quot;&gt;“BerlinGegen13”-demonstration&lt;/a&gt; and planned an art performance containing taking pictures of protest signs and confronting protesters about potential copyright violations of their signs - as the distopian future character “Copyright-Riotcop” that I portraied some time ago for the collectively written theater play &lt;a href=&quot;https://c-atre.de/produktionen/copyriot/&quot;&gt;“The Time is Right”&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The theater play is about time travel and a way over the top copyright, that acutally destroyes art itself. So pretty much, &lt;a href=&quot;https://juliareda.eu/2019/02/eu-copyright-final-text/&quot;&gt;what the upload filters may become&lt;a&gt;. So that is why I felt that this art intervention is very precise to the point.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Art is a way of free thinking and boundaries breaking social intervention. Art is widely understood as a performative construct. Art becomes art, when it is seen and recognized as art. There is no rule based logically explainable definition that can be applyed by algorithms.
Every intention in building filtering algorithms will fail to some degree. I say that as an artist but also as someone working for an AI startup. Machine Learning is basically pattern recognizion - however art cannot be detecte by patterns but only by context. So far there is no computer understandable way of context - and that will make it pretty much impossible for filters to detect art.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sadly I could not conclude the performance as the real police confiscated the main part of my costume as they claimed it would be a “passive weapon” and held me nearly one hour, so I missed a big part of the demonstration - and the chance for the actual confronting part of the planned performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is quite ironic that an art performance based on a theater play about repressions against artists was shut down at a demonstration about freedom of art. (Though the law used against this art performance has nothing to do with art or copyright. In the theater play the repressions against artists are copyright based too.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you happen to have taken pictures of me as Copyright Riotcop, please send them to me: gero [at] zweifeln.org&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However the protest signs I got to take pictures of were pretty awesome:&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 03 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2019/Copyright-Riotcop/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2019/Copyright-Riotcop/</guid>
        
        
        <category>photos</category>
        
        <category>art</category>
        
        <category>politics</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Offline Tags</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/General_Data_Protection_Regulation&quot;&gt;GDPR&lt;/a&gt; was set in place in May 2018 and since then it’s quite a debate how it’s still okay to take pictures at conferences.
My solution is a variation of &lt;a href=&quot;https://offlinetags.wordpress.com/&quot;&gt;“offline tags”&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2012 a Berlin based think tank developed a system of buttons to be automatically recognised by a software and edited (either face blurred or gave a note to not take a picture. The software worked only as a prototype demonstration - but the more interesting part for events is: you can give all attendants either buttons or stickers to mark themselves as either “want to be photographed” or “don’t want to be photographed”.
If there is a badge it could also be possible to have two versions of a badge with either “no photos” or “yes to photos” or some easy to understand symbol.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a photographer I’m happy to follow these rules and will take care that no face of someone with a “no photo” tag will be in any of the sorted pictures.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 12 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2019/Offlinetags/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2019/Offlinetags/</guid>
        
        
        <category>photos</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Jazz Dance Photos</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In June 2018 I had a photo shooting at Tempelhofer Feld with my jazz dance class, &lt;a href=&quot;https://evgenia-itkina.com/&quot;&gt;with our dance teacher of Evgenia Itkina&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 11 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2019/Jazz-Photos/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2019/Jazz-Photos/</guid>
        
        
        <category>photos</category>
        
        <category>art</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>AI and Consciousness</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Review: &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/selfawaresoup&quot;&gt;Esther Weidauer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talking about artificial Intelligence, one may ask “Can computers think?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We (=humanity) don’t really know how thinking works. There are lots of scientists working on it but it is complicated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To answer that question, Alan Turing created the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Turing_test&quot;&gt;Turing test&lt;/a&gt; in 1950(!) - but he changed the question to  “Are there imaginable digital computers which would do well in the imitation game?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So he doesn’t ask whether computer can think but whether humans can distinct between an answer given by a computer or another human being. If humans can’t say which answer comes from a human and which from a computer, the computer passes the Turing test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1966 Joseph Weizenbaum created &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ELIZA&quot;&gt;ELIZA&lt;/a&gt;, a chat software that mainly asked questions. It was seen by many as “intelligent”.
But it didn’t know or think anything but worked well on some pattern matching algorithm and therefore seemed to interact really with human beings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s when the distinction between &lt;a href=&quot;https://zweifeln.org/2018/Weak-and-Strong-Artificial-Intelligence/&quot;&gt;weak and strong AI&lt;/a&gt; got important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John Searle created the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chinese_room&quot;&gt;Chinese room&lt;/a&gt; as a thought experiment to illustrate the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a person in a room that’s totally locked from the outside, except for a letter box. Outside are some Chinese people writing questions in a letter and put in the letter box.
The person in the room doesn’t speak a single word Chinese - but there are books in that room that tell him exactly how to answer the letters in Chinese.
In these books a complex algorithm written down that tells exactly how to answer what question - without any explanation what the question or the answer means.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the person inside is able to answer the questions perfectly with help of these books and gives out a perfect Chinese answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Chinese people outside of that room believe the person in that room can speak/read/write Chinese. But actually that person just followed strict orders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John Searle uses this thought experiment as a metaphor for computers. Computers do that: they follow algorithms exactly and give answers to what they were asked.
However the computer may give out the perfect answer but doesn’t “understand” the question or the answer, as the person in the room didn’t “understand” what they were doing neither.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main question here is: how does semantics - meanings - evolve from syntax?
How do we &lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt; something?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That question is still widely unanswered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thomas Nagel’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/What_Is_it_Like_to_Be_a_Bat%3F&quot;&gt;“What is it like to be a bat?”&lt;/a&gt; is another think piece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He asks how it feels to hang all day long upside down in a dark place and go hunting by crying out loud and locate the prey by the bouncing signals of your voice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His point is: there are living things around that are so distinct from humans, we hardly can imagine to live like that. But even if we could, we still think from our human point of view. We could imagine to fly around and catch insects by a reflection of our voice - we can only imagine it from human point of view - not the one of a bat. We didn’t grew up as bats but as humans - so all our ideas are ideas within a human mindset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thomas Nagel is arguing for &lt;a href=&quot;https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Qualia&quot;&gt;qualia&lt;/a&gt; - the idea that every feel, every thought is to some degree fundamentally subjective and private. Similar to feeling pain - it’s a fundamentally subjective feeling. We can assume how pain might feel for someone in pain - but the exact feeling is only accessible to the subject.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s an approach similar to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ren%C3%A9_Descartes&quot;&gt;René Descartes&lt;/a&gt; “cogito ergo sum” - I think, therefore I am. If I’m doubting my own doubts, I thereby prove that I am doubting. And doubts need some entity to doubt - so I have to exist, too.
Even if I hallucinate and can’t trust my senses anymore - I always know that at least I am. (That idea is called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Solipsism&quot;&gt;solipsism&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The qualia idea that no-one really knows how it is like to be someone else than the subject opens the argument that maybe computers/robots/AI-systems do have that consciousness and a unique mindset (a quale - singular of qualia), too - and we (humans) simply don’t understand it.
If that’s the case we also never fully understand it, because a quale is fundamentally subjective and private.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the debate ends here because we simply can’t know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thinking needs consciousness, some kind of understanding symbols not just editing them. If that’s ever possible for computers? We don’t know, yet.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 26 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2018/AI-and-consciousness/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2018/AI-and-consciousness/</guid>
        
        
        <category>ai</category>
        
        <category>science</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Weak and Strong Artificial Intelligence</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Review: &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/I_Vinodh&quot;&gt;Vinodh Ilangovan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I see a lot of missing differentiation between weak and strong artificial intelligence in the public debate about AI nowadays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Strong AI&lt;/strong&gt; means, some computer/robot/AI-system has some level of consciousness. This idea is portrayed in many pop cultural sci-fi such as The Matrix, 2001: A Space Odyssey, Her or Westworld.
In sci-fi that make sense, as it is “science &lt;em&gt;fiction&lt;/em&gt;”.
However on the non-fictional realistic science part of it: nobody knows, what consciousness actually is and how it works, let alone how it might be rebuilt in some computer system.
So the Strong AI with its own free will is an impressive form of science fiction, as of now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are people who &lt;em&gt;believe&lt;/em&gt; that consciousness may evolve somehow out of computer systems. They have no explanation how that should be happening. Often they claim it will just evolve over a period of time. However the idea of consciousness evolving is quite old. Already in the 1950s and 60s some computer scientists believed such evolution of consciousness would happen within the next 10 years.
However, we have not witnessed this happen until today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In reality, consciousness did evolve in the past four and a half billion years - via evolution. So maybe it can happen again on a silicon based system; but that’s speculation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Weak AI&lt;/strong&gt; means a computer program is solving one problem on its own. Computers became pretty good at solving problems in an impressive fashion. This happens with in the software coded algorithms since the existence of software based computers. (Algorithms are like a cooking recipe: an instruction manual on &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; to come to an solution.) And in the past decades there  were tremendous success stories in that field. Calculators, Excel, the Internet, Google, Amazon recommendations, Boston dynamics robots - all of them belongs in the category of weak AI. All of them solve problems they were programmed to solve. Nowadays they often solve problems better than human beings (without access to a computer).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Artificial_neural_network#History&quot;&gt;1980s&lt;/a&gt; a new technology evolved, the artificial neural network. It’s meant to work similar to how neurons in a brain work together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4222327/&quot;&gt;Neuroscientists today talk rather about the Neuron-Glia-Network, as it’s not only the neurons taking part in decision making processes in the brain but the surrounding glial cells as well&lt;/a&gt;. The technological answer to that is the multi-layer neuronal network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s the technology used for autonomous cars, facial recognition and the face changing filters in Snapchat (and many other apps). 
Given the fact how little knowledge about functions of the brain we know, these systems bring impressive results - but it’s still not a brain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People believing in the self evolution of some kind of consciousness in computers often argue stating that neural networks are able to train themselves towards some kind of consciousness.
From the outside, this does look a little like it. A trained neural network doesn’t need much input to generate impressive outcomes (e.g. bunny ears on your head - even if you never showed your face to that app before).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These (multi-layer) neural networks are used in combination with each other a lot for different tasks so it seems they really do all kind of stuff on its own (e.g. the Boston dynamics robots getting up on its own after slipping, opening doors, carrying large items over rough terrain).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, for each of the tasks a human being decided what neural networks to put into which robot. So far no robot decided on its own what neural network it wants to install next - because so far none of the robots &lt;em&gt;wants&lt;/em&gt; something. They only do what they’re programmed to do - even if that happens to be very complex task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So to all of you who are afraid of some AI taking over the earth: it seems rather unlikely to happen yet. Our complete understanding of how the consciousness and willpower is created or generated is still missing.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 08 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2018/Weak-and-Strong-Artificial-Intelligence/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2018/Weak-and-Strong-Artificial-Intelligence/</guid>
        
        
        <category>ai</category>
        
        <category>science</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
